<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog of Dan Gustafsson</title>
    <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://academic-demo.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Blog of Dan Gustafsson</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Blog of Dan Gustafsson</title>
      <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The messy middle and how to make it data-sciency</title>
      <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/post/the-messy-middle-made-daty/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/post/the-messy-middle-made-daty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;googles-take-on-messiness&#34;&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s take on messiness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 10 years after the &amp;ldquo;Zeroth moment of truth&amp;rdquo; (dubbed ZMOT&amp;hellip; giggle), Google does a retake of the same ideas. Their research report: &amp;ldquo;Decoding Decisions, messy middle&amp;rdquo; came out July 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeling they want you to have after reading about the &amp;ldquo;Messy middle&amp;rdquo; is of &amp;lsquo;Charting undiscovered territory&amp;rsquo; (a headline in the text). However, they are not going as much upwind, as they would want you to feel. To prove that, let&amp;rsquo;s go back 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-zmot-that-came-before&#34;&gt;The ZMOT that came before&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rereading now, ten years after publication, ZMOT comes across as part marketing science and part marketing campaign tutorial. It&amp;rsquo;s also part &amp;lsquo;Digitalisation 101&amp;rsquo; course, with lines such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;now there’s no friction. You can pull out your mobile phone and look it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;people take the time to leave messages online about how much they love Scotch Tape. That’s because the effort is down to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;teach-the-old-marketing-dogs-about-digital&#34;&gt;Teach the old marketing dogs about digital&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ZMOT also included a whole section of counter-arguments to objections from marketing managers: “It doesn’t apply to my industry.” or &amp;ldquo;We already have a website. We&amp;rsquo;re doing fine.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One headline reads: &amp;lsquo;The rise of video&amp;rsquo; and contains this (prudent) remark :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s young adults have had mobile-phone cameras in their pockets since they were old enough to have pockets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other admonitions of hurry-up-and-get-digitalized read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’d never set up a corporate 1-800 number with nobody to answer the phone. (Would you?) &amp;hellip; The Internet is that 1-800 number, and it’s been set up for you even though you didn’t ask for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe they were aiming to open they eyes of old-school marketers. It&amp;rsquo;s a little paternal. But probably an effective communication mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-playbook-to-usher-digital-marketing-in&#34;&gt;A playbook to usher digital marketing in&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ZMOT makes for a great manual on how to sell SEO and ads to marketing managers! Like this: (1) Point to a changing world, (2) give a new model for marketing, (3) prove that it&amp;rsquo;s actually true, (4) counter any arguments, and then (5) give concrete advice on what to do. Finish with (6) a safari of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-messy-middle-update-versus-the-zmot&#34;&gt;The messy middle update, versus the ZMOT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what has changed since ZMOT? And what is new in the &amp;ldquo;messy middle&amp;rdquo; (shortened to MM here)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-basic-story-of-internet-shoppers-is-unchanged&#34;&gt;The basic story of internet shoppers is unchanged&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic story remains, in both the MM and ZMOT. Going from stimulus - into the internet - out via an order. The MM has a cleaner conceptualisation. And methods of actionability. The ZMOT was heavier on anecdotes and interviews with satisfied Google-customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The empiric premise in both texts are the same: &amp;ldquo;We asked a bunch of people how they shop online. This is what we found&amp;rdquo;. Also, a good part of the MM text goes through how to explore markets with Google Trends and the resulting conclusions with some 20 figures. In this sense, it&amp;rsquo;s partly &amp;ldquo;open&amp;rdquo; research (as in &amp;lsquo;open software&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;cognitive-bias-research-has-been-made-a-cornerstone&#34;&gt;Cognitive bias research has been made a cornerstone&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MM language &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; more academic, with words like &amp;lsquo;consideration sets&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;intersection&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;hypothesis&amp;rsquo;. These words don&amp;rsquo;t even occur in the ZMOT text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new jargon of behavioural science has heavily influenced the MM, like &amp;lsquo;reward system&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;cognitive inputs&amp;rsquo; etc. Specifically, the MM is more clear on how to influence the buyers using cognitive shortcuts while the ZMOT is more like a chatty mentor. The &amp;ldquo;cognitive biases&amp;rdquo; could be found (scattered and buried) in the ZMOT text, but now they form the bulk of a clearly though-out experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-others-say&#34;&gt;What others say&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few different opinions, &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@nickbarthram/googles-new-messy-middle-what-s-it-all-about-6a1a50be3df5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here for example&lt;/a&gt; where critics point out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the ethical sides of using cognitive biases (e.g. Darth Vader also uses these skills)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the simple fact that Google (in both texts) reaches conclusions favorable to their own search/ads products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.searchenginejournal.com/seo-messy-middle-purchase-journey/390575/#close&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; find that they&amp;rsquo;ve personally been ahead of Google all this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some have been teaching these very ideas for the last 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their big epiphany (whenever that happened) is that consumers/people are now empowered and not passive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most [here] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thedrum.com/opinion/2020/10/28/digital-marketer-s-guide-google-s-messy-middle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.thedrum.com/opinion/2020/10/28/digital-marketer-s-guide-google-s-messy-middle&lt;/a&gt;) seem to be in agreement that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Google study is a &amp;lsquo;fresh perspective&amp;rsquo; but might not &amp;lsquo;replace a good strategy&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-discovery-of-kahneman&#34;&gt;The discovery of Kahneman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thebearchitects.com/our-work/blog/decoding-decisions-why-marketers-need-to-master-the-messy-middle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The firm&lt;/a&gt; that Google collaborated with, seems inspired by Kahneman et al (using his language of System 1 and System 2 thinking on their web pages). Tversky and Kahneman&amp;rsquo;s book would, it seems, have been transformed into a specialist marketing company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-step&#34;&gt;The next step&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;m partly working in the field, I&amp;rsquo;m setting out to make a data science model of the MM. The model would be just a framework, to be filled with data from a specific marketing department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model data could be from various systems, but the model coefficients would reflect the specific customer behavior in the specified market under consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top, I&amp;rsquo;ll try to fit in the effects of interventions on the different stages. This is the usual focus of analytics, but I&amp;rsquo;m looking for a context that can also determine the effect size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method I plan to use will be predominately Bayesian on aggregated data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next post in this trail will be inserted here. So, stay tuned =)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS. Seems the &amp;ldquo;Messy Middle&amp;rdquo; title was inspired by this: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.themessymiddle.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.themessymiddle.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Output is the new black</title>
      <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/post/output-is-the-new-black/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/post/output-is-the-new-black/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-is-a-hands-on-business&#34;&gt;Learning is a hands-on business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once in a while I binge-watch youtube. Lately, it&amp;rsquo;s been Adam Savage and his builds. There is something soothing about watching active creation. I love tinkering and building, but not on his level (of obsession). I guess as a data-guy, the inner workings of the world is what drives me. Empiricist. And creating stuff with your hands is a part of that &amp;ldquo;hands-on&amp;rdquo; experience - I consider programming to be in that league.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to a lot of books lately, and has been amazed at how much things makes sense at the moment, and a week later it&amp;rsquo;s *poof* &amp;hellip; leaving just a wage notion of concepts, like waking up from a beautiful dream. A pop-lecture on youtube today &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; reminded me about what I have come to appreciate more and more with age: &lt;strong&gt;After you learn it, you have to make it your own, by actually outputing it back again.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ways-of-actually-learning&#34;&gt;Ways of actually learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic ways of actually learning something :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reflect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implement and use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;share with others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing more moocs and linkedin learning and what-not helps naught : I simply haven&amp;rsquo;t put in the time to reflect, implement and talk about it. All those hours have more or less been lost on me. That&amp;rsquo;s a hard lesson, right there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;love-matters-as-does-money&#34;&gt;Love matters. As does money.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all boils down to a simple formula for happy-as-a-clam-at-high-tide :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-mermaid&#34;&gt;flowchart LR;
  
  A((market demand));
  B((relevant skills));
  C((love doing it));
  A &amp;lt;--&amp;gt; C;
  B &amp;lt;--&amp;gt; C;
  A &amp;lt;--&amp;gt; B;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This models me as a carrot-driven (&amp;ldquo;love doing it&amp;rdquo;) knowledge worker (&amp;ldquo;relevant skills&amp;rdquo;) chasing the money (&amp;ldquo;market demand&amp;rdquo;). Not entirely untrue. However, at home with small kids, reading and listening (input) is easier, but without space to write or create (output). At work, output is mush easier to defend and input is not considered working&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Also: finding the right project at work that balances development of self, business value and client satisfaction is mostly an impossible triage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-savage-lesson&#34;&gt;The Savage lesson&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, time doesn&amp;rsquo;t wait, so this means a more deliberate, thorough, exercise when-ever I do learn something new. Reflect. Implement. Share. I wish this would have been imparted into my younger self, who lusted more for new sights than for mastery and power. I think that the lesson from Adam Savage is to &lt;u&gt;finish the build&lt;/u&gt;, and reflect and share honestly with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZVO8Wt_PCgE&amp;amp;t=943s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZVO8Wt_PCgE&amp;t=943s&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manager: &amp;ldquo;What if we pay them to upskill, and they leave afterwards?&amp;rdquo; HR: &amp;ldquo;What if we don&amp;rsquo;t, and they stay?&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
